<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An alarum for ladyes by the Sieur de la Serre, historiographer of France ; nevvly turn'd out of Franch [sic] into English by Francis Hawkins, dravving on to the tenth yeare of his age.</title>
            <author>La Serre, M. de (Jean-Puget), ca. 1600-1665.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1638</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 88 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 70 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10209</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20487.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S4841</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23955520</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23955520</idno>
            <idno type="VID">27009</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10209)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 27009)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1839:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An alarum for ladyes by the Sieur de la Serre, historiographer of France ; nevvly turn'd out of Franch [sic] into English by Francis Hawkins, dravving on to the tenth yeare of his age.</title>
                  <author>La Serre, M. de (Jean-Puget), ca. 1600-1665.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[9], 128 p. : port.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Chez Nicolas &amp; Iean de la Coste, au mont S. Hilaire, à l'Escu de Bretagne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>A Paris :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M. DC. XXXVIII [1638]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: [pi]⁸ A-Q⁴.</note>
                  <note>Includes frontispiece portrait of author at age 10.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: torn, with some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Women --  Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:27009:1"/>
            <p>AN ALARVM FOR LADYES.</p>
            <p>BY THE SIEVR DE LA SERRE, Hiſtoriographer of France.</p>
            <p>Nevvly turn'd out of Franch into English, by <hi>FRANCIS HAWKINS,</hi> dravving on to the tenth yeare of his age.</p>
            <p>A PARIS, Chez NICOLAS &amp; IEAN de la COSTE, au mont S. Hilaire, àl'Eſcu de Bretagne.</p>
            <p>M.DC.XXXVIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:27009:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>portrait of Francis Hawkins</figDesc>
                  <head>Francois Hawkins tirant a l'aage des dix ans.</head>
                  <head>Francis Hawkins about the age of Ten yeares.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <l>See here th' effigies of a Child whoſe witt</l>
            <l>So farr outſtripps his yeares &amp; ruderthronge</l>
            <l>That at Ten yeares he doth teach with whats' fitt</l>
            <l>For their behavour from a forraigne tongue</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:27009:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:27009:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27009:3"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE EDVVARD SAKVILE. EARLE OF DORSET, One of his Majeſtye's moſt Honourable Priuy Councell, Knight of the Noble Order of the Garter, and Lord Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlaine to the Queene's Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>IGHT HONOVRABLE,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Truely; though I am vnder tender yea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res:
<pb facs="tcp:27009:4"/>
yet my ambition ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re's ſo high, as to call your Excellence the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron of this my Treatiſe. My lovv degree, then myne age, to cenſure ſtrictly, alas, ſuite not properly, to offer vp aught in this nature vnto your Honour: Deigne though in your benigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to connive at this my boldneſs: for vvhich I cannot produce expreſs defence: vnleſs this may agree vvith your propi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſneſs,
<pb facs="tcp:27009:4"/>
that it may not ſeeme vnto you amiſs, to bee honour'd by each one, even from shrub to Cedar.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Right honourable,</salute>
               <signed>I take my moſt ſubmiſſiue leaue <hi>Your honour's devoted Servant,</hi> FRANCIS HAWKINS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:27009:5"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>ENTLE READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>The firſt Treatiſe I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented the vvith, vvas of good beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour. I had thy candor, favour, and honour, as a benigne receiver, of that my labour: vvhich encourag'd mee to vvaite on the againe, vvith another of an higher ſtraine, and of a rarer na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, allſo of a more vſefull matter. It vvas a Formulair of Compliments to bee expreſſed by voice, and Miſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue Letters, the one, and th' other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd vnder their proper Titles.</p>
            <p>In my Preface there annex'd, I ſaid; that I vvould preſent thee vvith
<pb facs="tcp:27009:5"/>
another Piece, and make my Poſy one, compil'd of three. Behold heere my juſt tender. Though this each vvhere agree not vvith thine eare: yet may'ſt thou heerein diſcover theiſe ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes vice even in perspicuous cypher. Fare-vvell.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:27009:6"/>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:27009:6"/>
            <head>AN ALARVM FOR LADYES.</head>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>The firſt Dayes Worke.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>WAKE yee, Ladyes, awake yee, at the dreadfull ſound or this Trompet. It's the ſummon of your apparance in the name of God, to that inevitable judgment, ſuch is it, to which all human Nature
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:27009:7"/>
muſt obey, muſt bow: It's a judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that aſtonisheth the moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, and cauſeth the moſt juſt to ſighe, yea rather through feare to tremble.</p>
               <p>Awake yee, forſake your, though nice coutches ſpeedily, come yee out of them, as if they were no other, then your graues, where the worme of your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences doth devoure yee; Heare attentiuely the laſt time, the finall decree of your ſafety or loſs, your liues, or deaths.</p>
               <p>Open your eyes to this dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full light of the Sunne, which this day ſendeth his beames ſoe bright into your chambers, which I may well enſtile dolefull; for who well knoweth, whether each ſtreame of this Planet, bee
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:27009:7"/>
not a funerall torch, which ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roundeth your beds, as your firſt coffins: ſince that our liues haue not in proper one ſole moment: Surely, it were to much purpoſe to number your yeares, the bells call on yee to the buriall of one of your company, much yonger alas! then are yee.</p>
               <p>How is it poſſible! that in the proper poſture wherein yee lye, yee once reflect not on your dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes, on your laſt end? Behold yee ſtretcht forth at lenght, to your vttermoſt extents, in that ſelf ſame linnens, which likely will ſerue yee in lieu of your winding sheetes. It's well indeed, that yee can breath as yet, this witneſs of your liues is the ſigne of your dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes: ſince that each reſpiratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:27009:8"/>
denote a minute of the clock of your lungs, vntill the laſt breath, the laſt ſigh, make yee know, the laſt hower of your retreits. And as all your other actions neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily returne thither; can yee bee ſenſible of life, without feeling your ſelues to dye, and dying void of thinking, that the ſelf ſame day which by grace hath been lent yee, may by juſtice bee your very laſt: where you muſt render a ſtrict account of each moment, which haue fore-run even from your births?</p>
               <p>At the lenght; behold yee riſen: but wherewith doe you enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine your pretious time; yee ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke your addreſs vnto your lookin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glaſs, and giue your ſelues the firſt, therein, by yee the day is
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:27009:8"/>
given over to the good morrow, to all th' inchantments of your fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re face, alas! It were requiſite, that ſome one, or other, should whiſper in your eares, as it was formerly to the wife of Mithri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dates, <hi>Sooner, or later death will at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend on you, it will come inevitably:</hi> Is it credible, that your bloods even frozen with feare, and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, become not changed into very ice, where ruines may bee plainely diſcovered by the entice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments whereby yee appeare ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latreſſes? This mighty, as vnhappy graced by beauty, made careſſes, and homage, as doe too many others of yee to her face, in her lookinglaſs, alas! even when shee was tould: that she muſt dye, there was newes indeed!</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:27009:9"/>How is it now Ladyes? doth not one daily ſing the ſelf ſame ſong vnto yee? were yee happy of the leaſt memory, it would certainely cauſe yee to reflect ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly, that there are very many of your companions dead; and I can aſſure yee, that yee trace them apace.</p>
               <p>Are yee confident to gaze on your faces with ſelf delights in your lookinglaſſes ever: ſince that beauty dooth flitt daily, daily fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, and giveth it's adieu? Yee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire with eyes idolatreſs, not weighing ſeriouſly, that your ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues are the ſacrifices lay'd vpon the Altar. This world at the mercy of the Deuine juſtice, the officer of wich is Time, doth though by ſlow paces, vsher yee to death,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:27009:9"/>
where yee muſt endure eternall paines for your offences.</p>
               <p>What curioſity ſee yee? what rare gemmes contemplate yee on in the lookinglaſſe, that there yee ſtay ſo long? Maketh it shew vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to yee, that your foreheads are as ſmooth as glaſs? alas! The one, and other hath deceiu'd yee farr: Your foreheads coutch their wrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kles vnder the vaile of your owne arts, for yee daily paint them; And beſides, your lookinglaſs, which flattreth yee, by a new de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe of the cunning artificer, who to oblige yee doth decypher yee ſuch as yee would bee, not the ſame yee are: what novelty ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire yee now? your eyes? It would ever grieue me, if they ouerflow not in teares, to deplore their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:27009:10"/>Is it your mouths? It ſuffiſeth mee to know: that they can not vtter words of more validity: then are theiſe which declare, and divulg the trueth of your calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes. And for your tinctures, deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cateneſs, they impoſe on me cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable ſilence fearing to wrong them by the ſole aire of my breath.</p>
               <p>Can I not impoſe ſilence with patience, on my ſelf as yet, that yee may reſt in peace, ſince that yee are ſeriouſly intertained ſo; Where there are found more drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes: then grounds, then reaſons, which I muſt needes beleiue? We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re yee awakened: then would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſound the direfull Trompet, which call's yee to the day of Doome: where each one muſt appeare in
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:27009:10"/>
proper perſon, and anſweare for himſelf in particular.</p>
               <p>Set before yee now the confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and diſorder yee shall bee brought vnto. Is it not likely, that yee will blush for shame: as often as yee haue lay'd white on your faces? will they not become pale with feare, as often as yee haue lay'd on them, red? therein, yee will betray your ſelues, publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quely diſcovering the ſecrets of your guilty ſlights.</p>
               <p>I excuſe Narciſſus in the fable, where as it's found that there hee became his own enamoured, the adorer of himſelf. How was hee deceived? Alas poore Narciſſus! thou never didſt diſcover thy ſelf in that guiſe, and manner: But how can one pardon yee? or in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:27009:11"/>
any wiſe conniue at the errours found in yee, of the like nature? Can yee make the leaſt queſtion of your defects: ſince that yee are fully fraught with them? And for your forgettfulneſs of your miſeryes: it's ſtrang! What yee fe'ele a thouſand times a day, can not butt make yee confeſs: that yee are not paſted of aught elſe, nor formed of any other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
               <p>Awake yee then ſpeedily, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme your ſelues out of this earthly ſloth, wherewith your ſoules are burthned, are indeed heavily oppreſſed, and lending an attentiue eare vnto the dreadfull ſound of this Trumpett, which ſummoneth the Vnivers to judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ponder ſeriouſly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that it
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:27009:11"/>
giveth not a vaine warning: ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce that each moment, an infinity of ſoules, come thither in trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes. See in what caſe yee would bee found: if death should ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe yee even then: when your faces are painted, your phanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyes charged with vanityes, and your ſoules ſoyled with a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand kinds of crimes: Oh God of juſtice, who will not feare thee, at the day of thy vengeance?</p>
               <p>Belieue me Ladyes; ſince that your death's are inevitable: ſince that yee muſt expreſſely dye in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed: ſollicitouſly note your day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly demeanours. It ſeemth to any one, who obſerveth the care which yee employ on your faces: that you liue for them onely. The faireſt of your company, who
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:27009:12"/>
yeſterday dyed ſuddainely to day affrighted her vaſſals, and though yee bee tender to maintaine her former beauty: yet I aſſure mee: that yee defye to come nigh her without ſtopping your noſes.</p>
               <p>Enſtyle yee thoſe horrours gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which appeare on her face? thoſe her eyes ſuncke? thoſe her wanne lippes? I tell yee truely; that hew of death, that it's tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, would as it where even make mee hate your ſexe: were I not a fruite of the ſame tree; The rootes, and body of the tree, are of the ſelf ſame ſtamp; The leaues and flowers, are of the ſelf ſame nature, there is not a pinne to chooſe.</p>
               <p>To apply my ſelf more nigh vnto yee, I will ſtate it thus; that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:27009:12"/>
there is amongſt yee one, who is the flower, the mirrour, the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of this age, what honour, what lucre, what returne of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitt will hence accrew vnto her? were it that one ſing her praiſes in each tongue: there will not be found aught; but aire in diuers fashions. Should one erect, and conſecrat vnto her Altars: she muſt bee the ſacrifice, for having been the Idole. Were it that shee could impoſe lawes to all mortalls: she can not exempt her ſelf from beeing ſubject to all their miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes. Were that courtly Fortune led her by the hand, to the height of thrones: the ſelf ſame may oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion her to fall, into the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipice of a lamentable priſon, there to dye through greif; as it
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:27009:13"/>
was to Darius his wife. Il'e goe further; namely; that herrenow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned beauty, had the vant in the judgment of many ages; what then? where may be found her aduantag therein? A thouſand ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours will bee aſcribed vnto her. What will the world render vnto her, where shee is no more, nor ever shall bee? and likely shee shall then burn in Hell, there ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine eternally. Her body I ſay, shall bee food for wormes. Her ſoule, for the flames, and ſomti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes her name, and fame shall bee celebrated heere below. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re lyeth the honour now? My ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits doe ſuffer, in theiſe contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plations, through their conceiu'd feare, and aſtonishment.</p>
               <p>Ladyes; in what a miſerable
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:27009:13"/>
condition are they; who ſolely haue beauty, for their share, for their part? What rate ſet yee on beauty alone? I ſay it's no other: then to haue a gay poſy of flowers, wherewith one may deck, and dreſs one's ſelf trimmely in the morning, during the ſpace that they are fresh: butt about noone, indeed ſo ſoone one leaueth the regard as well of the flowers: as ſtemme: even ſo, at the approach of night, this admired obiect, (the ſelf ſame ment) is miſpriſed of the Vnivers.</p>
               <p>Truely what ſoever is ſay'd; I find nothing good but Vertue: the reſt paſſeth by, and vanisheth. One of tall, and comely ſtature ſtoopeth. A cleere voice changeth. And a polite wit ſometimes loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:27009:14"/>
it ſelf through Vanity. Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue is it, which is ſolely ſtable, ſolely permanent on it's one ground, never giving vs over to our ruine.</p>
               <p>Bee yee then Ladyes, ſince ſo yee will needes haue it, as faire as was Cypris ſay'd to bee in the fable: yet yee will gaine but an apple for your recompenſe. Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitt yee bee as beautifull, as was Lucretia famed to bee in the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory, yet dyed shee through greif. All the beautyes, who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue appeared on the earth, ſince the inſtant of it's hauing beeing, make but à hillock of it's groſs duſt. It's vertue ſolely which lead's vs beyond our tombs.</p>
               <p>But whither goe yee now ſo well accoutred, ſo neately dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed?
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:27009:14"/>
If it bee to Confeſſion, to make that deſſeigne your good morrows; ſince that it's the firſt Sunday of the moneth: then reflect how yee haue prepared your ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues. In lieu of examining your conſciences before a Crucifixe; yee haue been curious to enquire the ſtate, and being of your faces before a lookinglaſs.</p>
               <p>Yee goe to craue pardon for your offences, and a new tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs yee, in the ſame which calls for juſtice. Yee part I ſay from the Confeſſion chaire to the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, there to receiue your Saviour with ſoules more diſpoſed to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend heere after: then reſolu'd to repent of what is paſſed in your former liues. Is not this to crye for vengeance againſt your ſelues.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:27009:15"/>Me thinckſt I ſee the rare ſainct Francis to appeare with that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect charity, which enflamed him on earth, and by the ſelf ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me fire wherewith the Seraphins are ſurrounded, and entertained happily in Heauen, and yet hee thought himſelf vnworthy to ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke vpon him the order of Preiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood: Yet will yee bee ſo auda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, ſo shameleſs, as to receiue your owne Creatour with im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure mouths, and prophane hearts; the ſole thought of this crime, doth put my ſpirits out of frame, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed through confuſion, and aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:27009:15"/>
               <head>AN ALARVM FOR LADYES.</head>
               <head>The ſecond Dayes Worke.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Warne yee Ladyes, in the name of God, for it's himſelf who giveth yee notice: that yee nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther know the day, nor hower, when this Trumpet, which cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth yee to his judgment will gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue the laſt ſummon. How is it
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:27009:16"/>
with yee? Thinck yee it not amiſs, to paſs the moity of your ages in dreames, and folyes? Yee ſleepe with ſoules as black, as Hell; what repoſe can yee enjoy at the eue of your everlaſting reſtleſneſs? The Heaven; though inſenſible, quaketh for horrour, at the cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, the great noiſe of this Trumpet. The earth; though im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooveable, doth thence tremble for feare; The Angells themſelues in their purity, and all the Saints jointly in their innocence, are toutched with aſtonishment; all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they are not capable of feare: and yet yee ſleepe, during the time of this publique alarum's being: which fright's all Nature. Awake yee ſpeedily, and prepare your ſelues to render an account,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:27009:16"/>
even of the leaſt idle word which yee haue let fall.</p>
               <p>Ah! how out of frame yee are; when yee wake, it ſeemeth to me: that yee haue ſet by to dye in shew, yee will dye now in earneſt. Let me ſee how it is with yee? Yee are at a bay for feare, and dread. Oh! how profitable would theiſe agonyes bee found vnto yee: if yee would oftenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes vndergoe the paines to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend liuely God's judgments: but your ſpirits avers'd from ſo ſerious thoughts, are the cauſe of your miſſpriſe thereof, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reflecting on your loſs ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, that's à pitty, alas!</p>
               <p>I perceiue, that yee are riſen to dreſs your ſelues, and yee are never vnready to deck your bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:27009:17"/>
repleat with infections: but forbeare a while I pray: then look out of the window; there's a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacle for yee to meditate on, that ſtinking carcaſs, which is carried to be buryed, the ſame with whom two dayes ſince, yee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted with for beauty, it's now as yee ſee, borne to the tomb; and yee will follow it thither: it's but a pace before yee; it's not knowen as yet wether yee arriue all three together thither: This dreadfull Trumpet ſoundeth day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and yee trace the ground in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſantly, and run the ſelf ſame race. Obſerue a right how it doth agree to judgment: that yee bee ſeen buryed in the way, one whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le; to friſle your haires for to hide your nitts; another time; to make
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:27009:17"/>
white your teeth, thoſe little bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: whoſe leaſt infected, ruineth your graces, and thus much is in favour of your bodyes: which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parantly doe putrify; and hence the wormes expect their prey in this world, and the infernall ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits in the other. What is the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefitt which your ſoules doe reape by the graces of your faces? Thinck yee; that at the hower of your deathes, your Confeſſour will demand of yee, how many yee haue enthrall'd, enchained, and made your ſlaues? No no, but at larg, namely; how long it hath been, that yee haue em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd your time in ſo vnhappy a beeing at ſuch rate, in ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſerable a ſtate: There is no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther talke of your excellent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:27009:18"/>
your rares faces; their gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces shall poſſeſs no places, no mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re shall they domineere: your ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les onely shall pleade their cauſes, God grant that they want not plea to obtaine their ſuites.</p>
               <p>O how faire is the employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this ſecond dayes enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment! it's paſſed off in admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and tricking your ſelues, meaning thereby to tempt and attrap weake perſons to idolatriſe! But, alas! I find yee farr, more ſimple yet. It doth appeare, that yee labour onely to advance and advantadg the fiends of Hell: ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce at the dayes end, they cary with them away all your ſpoiles. Further; heerevnto adjoine their conqueſtes of your ſelues. It's con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs'd, that yee are ritchely cloth'd,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:27009:18"/>
that there can not bee added aught to the ſtately curioſity which ſerue, as a new luſtre to your enticements: But whither bend yee your way ſo nicely deckt? if it bee to a Comedy.</p>
               <p>Ah! how Cleopatra, that young Princeſs, repreſenteth a dolefull perſonage, on the ſtage the Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of her marriage, in the Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedy of King Philip her deere huſband's death, for she dyed, by the ſame ſtroke of misfortune, which caryed that great Monark to his tomb. Shee was as faire as are yee. How comes it to paſs: that yee are happyer? She was as yong as yee. What reaſon haue yee not to apprehend her miſery, her miſsfortune ſenſibly?</p>
               <p>The Trumpet which cited yee
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:27009:19"/>
to death, and judgment, ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth inceſſantly, thither doth each one make their recours in troupes, and croudes. Who can aſſure yee, that yee shall not appeare there this very day: ſince that yee ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke your way as faſt as the reſt? Is that a repoſed life, is it to poſſeſs tranquillity, to perceiue your ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues dye without your beeing pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for death? will yee expoſe thoſe things to ſo great a perill: Which yee can not looſe but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce? Yee liue not but for Eternity: for the life of this world is not properly a life: and yet yee let paſs your time without reflecting, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce thinking of Eternity, which will laſt as long as God Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
               <p>What? will it not turne to your
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:27009:19"/>
reproach: that on Earth yee shall bee found to haue donne nothing elſe, but dreſs, and deck your bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes of earth? Oh! what a rare e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xerciſe would it bee: if ſo your ſoules were of the ſame matter! Oh! the ſweet entertainement: if it were not expreſſely neceſſary to dye! if ſo one were to liue for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver: but; daily to liue the eue of an eternall loſs, and paſſing all the time, to the dreſſing, and dec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of your carcaſſes; by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence it muſt follow: that Hell will bee your recompenſe.</p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding what heerein is fore delivered; behould yee paſs your time, in ſeeing a Comedy at the Burgugnion houſe: but know yee not, that yee there act your parts, and are at the end, of each
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:27009:20"/>
interclude, giving occaſion of laughter and ſcorn to all the ſage Democrites, for the vaine employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of your times? yet it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient, that I extract your gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, out of your loſſes. Atleaſt thinke yee, during this your en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainements of time; that the world is a Theater, where even new yee repreſent thoſe perſons whom God hath endowed for E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity: Doe yee well or ill; yee shall not appeare but this time ſolely on the Theater, yee play your parts for ever, the Angells, and the Diuells are your lookers on, expecting the end of the laſt act, whence yee are to receiue praiſes, or reproaches, I meane recompenſe, or chaſtiſement.</p>
               <p>Yee haue a faire petition to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:27009:20"/>
deliver, deſcended from the Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into your ſepulcher. Oh! gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue vs leaue to riſe againe, wee will liue better then in former times wee haue. The intercludes are paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. The play is ended. The can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dells are extinguish'd, each one shall receiue his guiderdon, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his merit, and for an Eternity. O fearfull judgment! But what'is more dreadfull yet, is that the Trumpet doth ſummon yee thither amongſt the diſorder wherein yee liue: I leaue yee to conſider heere on ſeriouſly.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:27009:21"/>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:27009:21"/>
               <head>AN ALARVM FOR LADYES.</head>
               <head>The third Dayes Worke.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>APPY are they, vvho reſt in our Lord</hi> Ladyes then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> yee: for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> I find yee, your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> are as black as poſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> though your faces <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:27009:22"/>
white. Behold yee are bridled vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the chinne, as are little infants with a mask lined with waxed linnen to fright them.</p>
               <p>Oh! how would yee bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazed, if yee muſt neceſſarily ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare before God Allmighty within a moment, to vndergoe the ſentence of his judgment? Which of either, ought to bee more deere vnto yee the beauty of your bodyes, or your ſoules healthes? Your bodyes, concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>u'd of corruption, and borne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the imperfection in which they liue, can they eleuate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, to make compariſon with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, created by the hand <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>llmighty, through his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> charity, and for his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:27009:22"/>Yet and againe, Oh! prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>galls of miſery, of infirmity, of meere weaknes indeed; who miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe nothing els but your ſoules ſafety; and are not paſſionatly tender for aught els, but for your bodyes. Them you adorne often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, with new clothes, with ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce robes; without weighing: that they conſume all which they toutch; and ruine all which decke them. Yee doe well to beſtow on them haire to adorne their bald heads, with a perrewig. The wrinckles on their foreheads, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke appeare atlenght, the borowed gally pot of roſes, to shew vs clearely, the thornes wherewith their age is ſtated in.</p>
               <p>Conſerue your beautyes with the art of limbeck, renew your
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:27009:23"/>
teeth each yeare, hidet your lim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and flaggy breſts vnder a handkercher, allſoe shrowd ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what, which may make them ſeeme round, and hard: the default of ſuch vpriſings would bee va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liew'd as a moſt apparant defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity; It would deſtroy all, Then; and Time, who trayleth along all things, who ſpareth none, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth an other breach, ſuch a rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne; which can never bee repair'd: I referre it to your quickned, to your more liuely ſpirits hitherto drowned with ſleepe, to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of your better reaſon long ſince ſtrayed; Whither this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of life, which yee lead on Earth, can conduct yee to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven?</p>
               <p>The third hower is even at
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:27009:23"/>
hand, at it's period, in all which time, yee haue been mervaillouſly ſerious, but in what? to put on your new clothes, and your bands according to the fashion: May I bee bold to enquire of yee what therein yee meane? If it bee to shew your ſelues at the Revells, and there to dance, make not haſt. It was tould mee: that shee, who mooved for that meeting, is ſurpriſed by a continual fever, and the ſmale pox. Alas! what a chang of Medaile: Yet faile not to viſite her. Her affrighting ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lady, will teach yee to deſpiſe the baits, inticements, and beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes which yee valiew ſoe highly. Yeſterday morning shee conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for the golden apple, with the faireſt found amongſt yee;
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:27009:24"/>
this euening the curtaine of her bed is drawen to hide her, for fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, leaſt that shee hurt her ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers: Oh rare Beauty! It's to flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thee too much, to compare thee to the wind, and to the ſmoke: for thow art (as it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth vnto mee) much leſs in va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liew.</p>
               <p>The Revells yet goe on, I mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne the dancing to which Nature even from your cradles invited yee, and to which, Time is the violin: for by it's continuall mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it trayleth vs all together, to our ſepulcher.</p>
               <p>I much doubt, leaſt the aire of this dance bee diſſonant to your eares: but how ſoeuer; yee muſt dance to it, there is no gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſay. Further; it's time muſt bee
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:27009:24"/>
kept ſtrictly, it's all in cadence, it's muſically compos'd indeed. Oh! obſerue well it's burthen, there hath been much care em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed on it: Each thing flitteth, and glydeth without ceaſing, beauty leadeth in cheif, as the moſt fraile moſt brittle. Yee may plainely ſee your shares, your lotts: yet muſt yee of neceſſity paſs the reſidue of the day in ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what, which may ſeeme to pleaſe yee: but I pray yee what is it? Yee are euen now very buſy; Yee court your ſelues in the loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinglaſs, as did the wife of Nero: Oh! ſayd this Princeſs, that I might dye firſt: rather then haue the leaſt diffigure on my face; shee conſidered not what then shee did, how she liv'd, nor what
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:27009:25"/>
shee ſay'd: when shee dayly ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de this prayer: that each moment, of each hower inſenſibly depriu'd her, and robd her, of parcell, of her rare beauty.</p>
               <p>Ladyes, it's not expedient, that yee craue earneſtly on Heauen, for that deſſigne: ſince that, all the inſtants of your liues, are ſoe many ſecret theeues, who ſubtle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rob yee of the principall, and moſt curious enticing draughts of your faces, I ſay ſubtlely begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in the bud, dawning, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther call it Sun-riſing of your age: yet thereof, yee take noe heed. By ſerious attention on their a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, is raiſed ſuſpition; and hence are they partly detected to be theeues: but in the evening they are expreſſly found no leſs,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:27009:25"/>
then publick Pyrats, who cary with them all away, together with your ſelues.</p>
               <p>Oh! is it not even ſo, what I now relate? that theiſe trueths ought to be ſenſible vnto yee; in ſuch ſort, and manner: as that yee should not euer meditate on aught elſe: ſince of ſuch like ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, and tender ſpeculations de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend your ſafetyes? for if yee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent vnto your ſelues this variabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, this inceſſant circumvolution, wherewith all things heere be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low are chained, and to be bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried one after an other within this whirlepoole of Time, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voureth all, and that yee turning the other ſide of this medaile, would ponder: that ſoules onely are eternall, would it bee even
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:27009:26"/>
poſſible, that yee shall not bee fully taken vp with the loue of Eternity?</p>
               <p>It's more then ſix thouſand yeares, ſince the Creation of this World, and it ſcarcely ſeemeth to bee one day. It's very true; that what's paſs'd, is ſuddainely for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gott: But Ladyes; this Eternity, where God is the limit, and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, is it which ſolely ought to entertaine all your affections, all your deſires, and apportion all your hopes.</p>
               <p>Bee yee pleaſed that even now I shew yee the meanes. It's all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to lend the eares of your phantaſyes moſt attentiuely, to this dreadfull Doomes Trumpet; where the share of your happy E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity, or vnhappy, is to bee
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:27009:26"/>
ſeen determinatly. Hope not a jot for favour there. Iuſtice will beare the Scepter: Truſt not to your conſanguinityes or affinityes, your vertues will bee your faſteſt freinds; Yee haue a great catch of them indeed, yee haue a rare plea, to ſay: that yee are the daughters of a Prince, the wifes of Kings, and the mothers of Emperours: all theiſe circumſtances ſerve you to your ſepulchers. Your works ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lely accomplish all your honours: or your infamyes, all your felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes: or your miſeryes.</p>
               <p>Oh! Ladyes, how it's to bee great perſons, and happy on earth: yet there to pretend not aught. Thoſe who are borne, who are deſtined for Heaven, naturally haue ſuch a diſguſt of Earth: that
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:27009:27"/>
thereon they ſpinne out their ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me: as if they had no beeing the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re at all, ſtill lifting vp their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and their thoughts to this E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity: as to the onely good, the ſole Sanctuary. The fruition of it, is able to ſatisfy their deſires com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleately.</p>
               <p>O Eternity! thou art ſingular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gracious vnto mee: that thou receiveſt favourably my good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, my well meanings. I will never ceaſe to meditate on thee. Oh Eternity! how benigne haſt thou been to mee in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, well may I ſay; in making mee applye, all the abilityes, all the facultyes of my ſoule, on the meditation, of thy longanimity; in ſo much: that I shall never ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue other obiect then Thee, no
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:27009:27"/>
other ſight then ſpeculating on Thee. Doth it not follow neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſairily, that I loue thee entirely: If I abhorre all that flyeth thee, that forſaketh thee? If I ſeriouſly miſpriſe each tranſitory: am not I conſtrain'd to eſteeme thee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly? Let no man ſpeake to mee but of Eternity: each crime, not returning to the ſame, diſpleaſeth mee, nay rather; doth mee nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble injury. In a word; if there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bee any taken ſenſibly with aught, by how much the greater it is: the more doth it's exceſs menace vs of it's privation. Preſuppoſe La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes, that in this world yee bee both faire, and ritch; It's much. But I pray tell mee, what is their permanence? Had I to diſpoſe of an age: I would alow yee to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:27009:28"/>
the full terme of it: But at the laſt moment; what would remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne vnto yee? What would accrew vnto yee? your beautyes would not ſubſiſt: but in your owne tranſitory times, and your trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures though now poſſeſſed, shall bee farr from yee, as conſtrained to abandon them for ever. Your caſes are thus; all the goods of Fortune which yee enjoyed, chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging their names, propertyes, and natures will afflict yee, to thincke of. It's truely even ſo: that it's ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lely Eternity, which can quenche our hearts continuall thirſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:27009:28"/>
               <head>AN ALARVM FOR LADYES.</head>
               <head>The fourth Dayes Worke.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HAT ſay'd the wife of Roſidates to her ſelf, with a voluble tongue, and very nimble, as paſſionate in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed when she heard the dolefull Trumpet ſound at her doore, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnifying
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:27009:29"/>
vnto her the decree of her death, by the command of her brother King Hertodorus.</p>
               <p>Oh! Ladyes, how much mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re dreadfull is that Trumpet which doth ſummon yee to God All<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightyes judgment. This Roſida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes liv'd, and dyed a Heathen: but yee, who are deſtin'd for Heaven, will yee paſs your times on Earth, ſolely for Hell? It will ſoone bee noone by the watch of your li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, as well as by the town clock it ſelf: Where is your dayes work? If in ſuch ſort yee paſs the reſt thereof careleſly, either ſleeping, or beſotting your ſelves, it will be found at lenght: that yee liv'd here in this world no otherwiſe, then dreaming, and that in the other there, yee shall liue perpetually
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:27009:29"/>
awakened, amidſt the heates of eternall flames, everlaſting fire.</p>
               <p>Perceived yee not clearely, that the Sunne the other day, blamed yee notably, and ſuch like ſloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full people as are yee? but yee ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the leſs, will make it as your happineſs to ſleepe and drouſe. This ſtarr, which meaſureth the moments of your liues, leaveth not a whitt to run his wonted ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, his cours to traile yee to your graues.</p>
               <p>Rouſe your ſelves vp. Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber yee not, that yee are invited to a ſolemne feaſt of marriage? I muſt needes waite on yee; bee it but onely to obſerue your car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riadge. Il'e take notice of your va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nityes, and giue account vnto the world how fantaſticall yee are.
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:27009:30"/>
Take yee your time to dreſs your ſelues; in the meane while, Il'e contemplate ſomwhat, and alſo exerciſe my patience.</p>
               <p>Let mee approach vnto yee nigher. To what vſe are thoſe gally potts of pomada, thoſe bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xes of pouder, thoſe violls of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtill'd waters, and thoſe papers of vermillion, which I ſee vpon your cabinets by your night dothes? Is it a part of art, which yee put in practiſe, to make yee ſeeme mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re faire then yee are, in deſpite of Heauen, and Nature? Oh! what bitter. Oh! what ſalt teares will theſe vanityes extract from yee Ladyes. Bee it, that your Ladi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipps haue the leaſt leaſure lent yee to repent yee.</p>
               <p>It's to be granted: that your
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:27009:30"/>
bodyes doe daily require the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of pomada, of rare odour, to cover the defects of your teints. Your treſſes can not hide their greaſineſs without pouder. Your tawny-dusky faces after they ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue been made happy by the Alim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beck, expect the vermillion; leaſt that their dead colour appeare not at all: but yee obſerue not that yee labour to fill pots, which are perced; as did the Danaides.</p>
               <p>Where shall one find Pomada, which may agree with yee, and contend with your ſtenches? What is that pouder, that can dry the clammy greate of your heads? What water can ſerue the fullneſs of your deſires? And what ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>million can make appeare on your cheekes, which Nature hath not
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:27009:31"/>
planted there? Thence yee diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver plainely: that your actions containe in them ſolely vanityes, for their obiects. They reſt vnto yee for your recompenſe. Oh what braue conqueſts! yee looke not after aught but airery toyes; your heades are full of crotchetts. Yee like nothing, but what is ſmoke, witneſs the teares diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd on your eyes. See what'is the fruite of the courſe of your li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, behold the guiderdon which doth attend yee at the end of your race.</p>
               <p>Oh! how pretious was the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mada of Saint Elizabeth, who made vſe of it to parfume the fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, of whom? of the indigent! the poore! Oh! how odoriferous was the pouder, and the ashes
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:27009:31"/>
where Saint Marie the Egyptien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne covered her head, the day of her penitence! Oh! how the tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res of her repentance where rapt, and poſſeſs'd with Devine vertue; in ſo much as, her body, and her ſoule in an inſtant were embelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed! Oh! how ſtrang it is; the blush of her shame for her ſinne, was farre more liuely: then what yee daily vſe. Grant me this boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne for my paines hither to ſeen, no leſs I beſeech yee; to breake your lookinglaſs, which dayly flatter yee; nor ever take to yee other, then ſuch as I deliver vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to yee heere.</p>
               <p>Yet; thus much ſay'd, yee will keepe on your wonted wayes. Now yee are dreſs'd. Now at the feaſt, and ſuddainly will all
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:27009:32"/>
varietyes of ſweetmeates bee ſeru'd in: there is the end. What I would put into your minds, is; that all ſolemnityes haue but their times. On Earth, a feaſt is not to bee had: but of the fruits of its own garden; and as theiſe fruites, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue nothing proper, but their cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption: even ſo that aliment from day to day, doth naught elſe, but increaſe your infections; they can never ſatisfy your appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tits. The ſucceeding day, yee will ſenſibly find the vanityes of your pleaſures had at table: ſince that they vanish with the table cloth it ſelf.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe; ſeriouſly ponder, when yee are amidſt your jolli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes: that the ſelf ſame howers which yee haue employ'd in the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:27009:32"/>
pampering of your carcaſſes, are regiſtred in the ſcrole of their rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, ſince that whither yee eate, or laugh, Time leadeth yee to your tombe.</p>
               <p>Theiſe are the banquetts of Cleopatra, which are ſolemnely celebrated: though in shipps even floting: hence learne wee, that each where wee chang fortune, through the perpetuall decline of our liues, all our actions tend thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, what deſtroyeth vs, is ours in proper.</p>
               <p>But to goe on; in concluſion; behold your retourne vnto your houſes, the dance is ended, like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the feaſt. Oh Ladyes! me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate a little ſpace, but attenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vely I beſeech yee humbly on this paſſage, this phantaſyes, All theiſe
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:27009:33"/>
paſtimes, theiſe wordly pretty to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yes ſymbolize, are of the like na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture with theiſe dances, and feaſts, each of them flitte inceſſantly, it's ſure that death approatcheth nigh howerly. Were all your dayes ſpent in the ſolemnityes, which frequently are found, when ſo that marriages are pompouſly ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated. Oh! how direfull would your laſt day appeare vnto yee! ſince then muſt yee render ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of your time paſt in laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and dance! Reflect a while how many are the dances, and feaſts wherein you haue entertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned your times; hence take coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile ſecretly of your memoryes, then vſe your judgments, and ſee, what is left vnto yee: yee shall never haue other for your plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures!
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:27009:33"/>
And what? will it not bee reproach vnto yee: that yee ſould your portions for nothing, which yee pretended for Heauen? I ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue heard ſay, that Lyſimachus did exchang his Crown for a glaſs of water: but when? Ladyes, obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue then; it was ſo with him at that time, when hee was even as it were reduc'd to ashes, by the ſame heate of thirſt, which bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n'd his entrailles, in ſo much as beeing in ſuch plight, in rendring his dying ſpirit hee chang'd naught elſe but wind, but breath for water.</p>
               <p>But to ſee how remiſſely yee giue over your pretenſions of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall conſolations, of everlaſting joyes for toyes, ſuch I may truely terme them, which beare no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:27009:34"/>
titles; then of meere depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uations, of your phantaſyes, of your imaginations. Where is that ſelf affection whence yee ſeeme to become ſo paſſionate? Is it not to hate your ſelues: that you af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect not aught elſe: but what doth flit? it's not it? when yee dye, what will bee left yee of your paſſed time, but a preſent greif, and too late; ſuch; whoſe angui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shes will never ceaſe?</p>
               <p>Yee never dreame of other thing: then to enquire after new paſtimes, to the ruine of your ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes. Alas! Nor conſider yee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right: that Time doth ruine yee? for in ſeeking to paſs it, yee muſt find death. How ſo? is it poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: that yee ſtriue to paſs over it, which ſo ſwiftly glideth by yee,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:27009:34"/>
as doe your phantaſyes, light though they bee, they can not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver take it. And what more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly, yee ought to ponder, is, that all the time of your liues, hath for its terme, its limit a ſole moment, on wich, though ſuch, doth depend for ever, and a day your calamityes, or your felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes; that's a miſery in torment: which hath no end, this a bliſs in glory: which will be permanent, beyond all ages, illimited in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed.</p>
               <p>Oh! how pretious are the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templations, of the laſt period of our liues! How! is it ſo? that thou art not as inſeparable to our ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les: as is the shaddow to the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy? Oh! how ſweet is the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of our death! Why is it ſo?
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:27009:35"/>
that our memory is not for the moſt part, in ſuch ſort all taken vp with thee: as that it never for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get thee? Oh Deuine is the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation on Eternity! Art thou not as ſenſible of our ſoules, as our reſpiration is of the preſeruation of our hearts? How Dauid liketh mee well, when hee cryed out aloud, that hee had often medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated, and that ſeriouſly indeed on the dayes for ever: where God Allmighty is ſolely the light! Oh faire dayes! I wonder not: that yee haue no night: the Sunne which sheweth it ſelf on yee is bright, and borroweth not it's light: no. Oh dayes moſt happy! ſay no more; or thus: I am not one whit aſtonished, if ſo bee it that yee remaine for ever: the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:27009:35"/>
Planet which gaue yee a beeing, poſſeſſeth Eternity in cheif, in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. Truely, my ſoule is extaſyed, rapt as it were, in this ſweet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation, with ſuch ſingular content, it's in ſuch guiſe as that really it hath no deſire to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe.</p>
               <p>Ladyes, in a word, it's ſo; that yee muſt arriue to the dayes end, and returne thither from whence yee came in the morning: for it's but one dayes iourney. Yee haue a fine time of it to bee lazing. The Sunne, who ſendeth forth his bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes for yee, will that yee goe as faſt as doth hee.</p>
               <p>Dance, laugh, ſleepe vntill noone day; the shippe of your li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues leaueth not it's cours, it ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth evermore, inceſſantly on the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:27009:36"/>
ſea of it's proper miſeryes, onely by the wind of your reſpirations; it cannot ſtay it ſelf: vntill it arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue, at the hauen of the ſepulcher: Ladyes, it's the hauen to which Doomes Trumpet doth ſummon yee. Take yee heed, leaſt it bee not found a rock vnto yee: where yee may encounter too dreadfull a shock, the calamity thereby is for Eternity, and repentance vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable. In good earneſt, at what time ſoever I think of Eternity: nothing that's wordly, doth pleaſe mee. I am not bold to ſay ſo much: that each parcell of the Vniuers made ſuch by a Soveraigne power and abſolute from it, having it's ſoule, it's beeing, it's life, is not in it ſelf admirable, and adorable in it's Creatour: but; as there are ſo
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:27009:36"/>
many obiects of change, or of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption; my heart not well appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>s'd, ſigheth after the fountaine of the leſſer ſprings as after it which is onely capable to quench the thirſt of my deſirs. Ladyes, would yee but diſtaſt the word's pleaſures, yee haue a ready way to fill your beſt thoughts, on the delights of Eternity: for ſuch is the inequali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: that common ſenſe will lead yee will ſuffiſe, to make yee miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe them, and earneſtly deſire theiſe.</p>
               <figure/>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part">
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:27009:37"/>
               <head>AN ALARVM FOR LADYES.</head>
               <head>The fift Dayes Worke.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>OME to my ayde, my Lord, cryed out Saint Hierome a thouſand times a daye: I dye for feare at the reſound of that Trumpet, which doth ſummon mee to thy judgment.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:27009:38"/>Ah, Ladyes; if this glorious Saint, amydſt the deſerts, and amydſt the auſterityes of a life, all devoted to pennance, found himſelf reduced at a bay, at a ſtand for feare, and dread: can yee fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me with the vanityes of the world: when yee doe but once meditate on the neceſſity of your deaths, from which there's not one e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xempt? This innocent doth trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at it! and are yee not aught ſenſible of it? This harmeleſs qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes! perſiſt yee ſenſeleſs? This juſt man, I ſay againe cryed out inceſſantly for help, and ſuccour: though hee where ſoe pure! yet will yee not bee awakened: though infirme, by the example of his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtonishment? Can yee take reſt in the ships of your bodyes, and on
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:27009:38"/>
the world's tempeſtuous ſea's: without fore diſcerning that Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, who is the Pilott, puts yee one the shore of your ſepulcher? Awake your ſelues then ſuddai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nely, and as your liues are but dreames, at your waking dreame againe what trades yee intend to vſe, whilſt yee are in this long E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity, to which yee make your howerly approatch.</p>
               <p>God hath giuen yee, and each one of yee, ſince the time, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in yee haue been of reaſon a pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cill in your hands, as to Zeuxis, that renown'd Painter, who pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted according to his beleif, n'aught elſe but Eternity; this is a paterne for yee, ſuch; as it sheweth yee: that all your works should haue for object, and ayme, no other
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:27009:39"/>
thing. In ſumme; all which yee meditate on, ſay, and doe, is pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in oile colours of Eternity. I would yee vnderſtood mee aright, all approacheth nay endeth cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondent, to the good, or ill, either to the glory of your happy Eternity, or to your vnhappy E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity.</p>
               <p>If yee dye, as yee liue, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in bed vntill midday, what can I ſay? but that if ſo you play your time away, your lazineſs will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paint yee, and liuely expreſs yee for Eternity: where endleſly yee shall ſuffer paines.</p>
               <p>Allthough each one ſwill as hee will; it's but for his time, his dayes courſe, and at his owne expenſe. But one judgeth not of price of the good, or ill, or default in bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:27009:39"/>
merchandize, elſe where, then in the other world. Prepare your ſelues to vndergoe the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>Yee will even ſuddainely appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re dreſs'd, and trick'd according to the fashion of the time, and court: and how is't? Your fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers falling on your eares, ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>million on your cheekes, and flyes on your chinnes. Theiſe are not in vaine vndoubtedly, their deſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnes are to entrappe ſome one, or other: but at the daye's courſe run, it will then appeare vnto yee clearely: that yee haue made your ſelues whoopes, taking not the leaſt notice of aught elſe, but va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; as if yee had not thereof too much.</p>
               <p>I waite on yee at your ſally
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:27009:40"/>
from dinner, to your coatch, it's to aſſiſt you tenderly, and with humble reſpect indeed, it's my duety, and to attend you ſeriouſly with my thoughts, in your wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, with intention to obſerue, whither your times intertaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments prooue more vſefull: then delightfull.</p>
               <p>It's neceſſary that I exerciſe my patience a while, vntill the hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes bee harneſſed, and put to the caroche: allſoe, yee muſt hauey our time to looke on your ſelues agai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, while yee attire your ſelues with hoodes, and maskes. But oh! what ſimple imaginations en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine your ſpirits therein? There you inſtruct your eyes the art to tyrannize, and with ſtrang craft, to hurt many hearts, not refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:27009:40"/>
aught; that your ſoules re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue a ſtaine, through the vaine lightneſs, which thence remaine in them: It's there I ſay, where you invent new leſſons to allure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; ſo farre as to teach men, to make your ſelues beloved, and ferred at once, and the ſelf ſame time; and covertly pretend: that yee attend no end, while therein none, alas! none. Obſerue theiſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re deſſignes; what doe yee medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te on oftner? Let it bee that your black eyes with their vyes doe much hurt to day; to morrow, one drop of rume indeed, will make them red, which will ſerue to cure the ſmarts, of thoſe your former darts. How happily doe your courteous ſweetneſs, with your graces, acquire loue, and feare
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:27009:41"/>
iointly. Whoſoeuer they bee, that ſeeme to dye for yee, they loue yee not: it's; for what? for their intereſs, not to bee ſpoken of here further. Thus much yet will I ſay: that they who court yee as ſincere lovers, ground them ſelues on the expreſs ruines, the vtter deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of your reputations; and yee take it well, to make them feare yee. They care for nothing more: then to paſs their times, in that entrepriſe, their delights, their ſports.</p>
               <p>But it ſeemeth no leſs vnto mee: then that yee take your way to the race, to the place in vſe now a dayes. Oh! how vainely hunt you after toyes in this your walke, as to a publick faire where merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe is ſet forth for each to buy?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:27009:41"/>Would yee not ſay, tkat this yong ſimple fondling, cloth'd in green, who is like vnto tapiſtry, which yee haue ſeen frequently, hung before a doore, hath emplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yed about her face all her white<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning? Shee thinketh, that in beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty shee doth ſurpaſs, the Vniuers. Alas! for pitty. I ſpeake plainely to her now, not taking any notice, that her ſelf-loue daily putteth on a hood to ſee at randome her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects. Shee, who would bee the beloved'ſt of many, in each doth mooue pitty for ſuch her foly. My opinion of her, is no other: then that shee is a gloweworme, who giveth light to many from a dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghill, the ſurface of which is all covered with ſnow.</p>
               <p>What character shall this proud
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:27009:42"/>
piece beare? What may one's cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure bee heere of this giddy one, who beeing poſſeſſed of n'aught elſe but of a boſome, maketh a shameleſs bravado, as if the reſt of her carcaſs, were to bee let or ſould out right? Oh peace a while! what will prooue her confuſion: when the daye hath run its race? when shee muſt needes shut vp her shopp, having not met with any cuſtomer who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſoeuer, not one admirer of her treaſure? Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty is it, which hath enticements not found els where; there-in onely.</p>
               <p>I pray yee ſtay not a jot, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me hither ſpeedily, bee the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctatours of this fond toye, this Foppe. Whoſe beſt draughts through age, are become void of
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:27009:42"/>
moſs, and hence borrow for the ſtage, the artifice of ſo many flyes, as if they could nippe ſome one or other, though ſuch bee her age; a ſtrang paſſage: but commiſerable: for it's even ten yeares ſince that beauty bid her the laſt adieu: and if shee daily employ all her ſtudy for it's recovery: what foly would it appeare, to weare time preſent, for to call time paſs'd, againe: yet might shee bee happy in her diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters; were it ſo; that though shee ſuffer shipwracke: yet that at lenght shee take hold of vertue, to redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me her ſelf from danger, nay ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, from vtter loſs.</p>
               <p>Haue yee but a little patience to view the Lady who cometh in a coatch all guilt; by her counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and demeanour, I gueſs:
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:27009:43"/>
that shee doth eſteeme her ſelf, to bee the I dole of eache one, who behold her with attention, not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flecting aught on Time, her new coatch-man, who waiteth on her, it's hee, who beareth her in the ſame carre of triumph, to the aultar of her ſepulcher, there to be offer'd vp with shame together, with all her adorers.</p>
               <p>But shee that's there, how miſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bee-ſeemingly doth shee lend her eare, and attentiuely, to the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlings of a giddy humoriſt, who courts her, and yet; what is much more vndiſcret; she believeth all the lyes the braine-ſick delivereth vnto her. Mee thinkſt I plainely heare him ſweare: that shee hath the rareſt aſpect, and moſt admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redſt eyes, that ever did appeare
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:27009:43"/>
in this hemiſphere, and ſolely on the confidence, shee hath given to her lookinglaſs, she doth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue him.</p>
               <p>In the meane-while; heere are found braue aſſurances, rare cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions indeed. Ah how is it now? doth shee not know, that the firſt oath of an amorous, is to obſerue not one during the time of his paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion? And further it's the common fashion of lover's ſpeaches, it's their aire, to ſay to their Miſtreſſes: that they are mervailouſly faire, even to perfection, theiſe are their cuſtomary wayes, now a dayes: and yet moſt vnhappily; it's to bee deplored truely, yee ordinarily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue them, nor reflect yee aught: that your firſt betrayer, is your lookinglaſs, it alas, for pitty!</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:27009:44"/>Yet will I grant, that shee is rarely endow'd, and ſingulerly graced with beauty: there is the ſeat of her vanity. Could there bee added ſenſe, and life vnto her counterfaite, her picture; shee would thereby by many a degree ſurpaſs the Prototype, the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall: for that luſter may bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd as her proper: this hath no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in peculiar, but the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of decay. In ſo much; that when one perſuadeth her, that shee is mervailouſly faire, shee should take theiſe as ordinary diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes: ſince her beauty paſſeth by, is of like nature to the prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, which are given her, meere aire.</p>
               <p>Will you haue more of her? It's true; that shee hath the faireſt
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:27009:44"/>
eyes, that ever the world beheld: but when? when they are cleare, after dinner, and why not befo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re? Il'e giue yee an anſwere; The mornings entertainment is to take care of her gummy eyes, or eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>browes. There can not bee ſeen a noſe better shap'd, then is hir's: I confeſs it: but shee muſt haue ſupplied vnto her, a cleane hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kercher, and that every day. I muſt likewiſe ingenuouſly averre; that her mouth is very little, and pretty: but it's too ſtreight a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage for her ſtinking breath. Her complexion is delicate, even to perfection, it's evidently ſeen: but thus much is ſay'd, to the end, that shee might apprehend all things. The Sunne, the Fire, the Aire it ſelf, are her enemyes, which
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:27009:45"/>
make a perpetuall warre againſt her, vntill Time hath donne his worke, whereby shee may bee hidden vnder earth.</p>
               <p>Shee hath an excellent wit, doubt yee not therof a whit: for shee vttereth rare, and curious paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages; it were much better: that shee would apply her ſelf to pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to goodneſs. One doth enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re of workes: rather then of words. What is it to purpoſe, if shee haue a faire manner, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanour in ſpeach, the true meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re of her deeds shall judg her. She ſing's admirably well. Had shee n'aught elſe but her voice; shee could not enthralle otherwiſe: then by the eare: they who haue not affaires wherewith to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine their times, in paſſing by for
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:27009:45"/>
their pleaſure, would giue eare vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her: but when shee maketh an end of her ſonges, they begin to meditate on ſomething. Il'e ſay no more. If ſoe it happen, that there bee praiſes of her, given vnto her, they will returne the aire which she hath lent them. Iudg yee whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther shee will bee well content. In ſumme; let her bee ritch as was Semiramis, and more faire then Hellen. The one confeſs'd on her Epitaph, which shee caus'd to bee engraved on her tomb-ſtone; that she never poſſeſſed aught in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, when shee had her treaſure: but corruption, and miſery. The other; after shee had entrapped inſenſible hearts by her ſubtle charmes, ſtrook pitty vnto her greateſt enemyes onely hearing
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:27009:46"/>
of her miſfortunes. Ladyes, flatter not your ſelues. One ſighe of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance for your vanityes, will yeild yee more glory, and more benefit: then all the teares yee can make your enthrall'd ſlaues poore forth. In the meane while night warneth yee to retreit: behold your dayes journey at an end; now render account vnto your lookin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glaſs, of the number of your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts. But in earneſt how treate yee with it? It's true, that yee haue made many an one ſighe; if yee bee proud thereof, the aire will remaine with yee; n'aught elſe haue they return'd vnto yee. They haue ſayd true: that yee are very faire: it's enough for yee to shew your ſelues, at the window, and there to remaine a while, in
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:27009:46"/>
the evening's aire to giue eare to the harmonious Salute, the ſere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nade in fashion: which is offred vp vnto yee; longer yee will not bee: leaſt your cheekes bee ſwol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len by defluxion. Iudg yee then, without flattring your ſelues, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther one can loue yee long: ſince that ſolely your beautyes are the cauſes that yee are eſteemed of at all.</p>
               <p>How many haue I ſeen of theiſe Idolatreſſeſs of their own beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes, who after they had made pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliquely profeſſion to enthrall the hearts of the moſt inſenſible, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue come atlenght to ſuch diſtreſs, to ſuch miſery through their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity: that they were ſoe farre from beeing beloved: as that they proved rather an affright to the
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:27009:47"/>
world, rather deſpis'd, then pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty'd. Truely, Ladyes, if yee knew to how many accidents your beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes are ſubject, it would be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to yee perpetually, rather the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of your neglect, and miſpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe: then of your wonder. I deny not, but that it's one of the mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter-pieces of Nature: yet the ſelf ſame is become a ſtepdame, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it ſelf over to a thouſand ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of miſcheifes. It's true indeed, there is not aught more Divine on Earth, nor more enchanting: but this Divinity is alike to that, which one doth attribute to Alexander the Great, whoſe blood trickling out of his veines, shamefully pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faned all the Aultars which were dedicated vnto him: ſuch are theiſe charmes, they are meere illuſions
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:27009:47"/>
which deceiue, and abuſe weake ſoules.</p>
               <p>Verily, Ladyes, yee muſt come to this point; that is; to belieue, that vertue ſolely hath allurements, and graces, which are approv'd by Time, and Death. All the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticements, and all the charmes of Nature are by degrees deſpoil'd, together with it ſelf. And though it ſeemeth to conſerue it ſelf: yet by it's proper ruine finding it's eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tablishment in it's decay. Time ceaſeth not to abbreuiate from hower to hower the terme of the others raigne, whilſt hee dooth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume himſelf. In ſuch ſort; that for your comfort, all that yee ſee, doth vanish with your ſight. All what yee heare, doth diſperſe it ſelf with the aire, wherewith your
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:27009:48"/>
eares are filld, and ſo for the reſt, without that there bee aught found permanent on Earth.</p>
               <p>Ladyes, it's ſolely Eternity, which changeth not, it's it which doth remaine as long as your ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, and your ſoules, as long as it. Whereſoever yee take your cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, it's immeniſty will fill all, and it will bee the bounds of your af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires what ſoever they bee: After one hundred thouſand yeares, it will not bee an inſtant of Time's permanence, after one hundred thouſand millions of yeares, that inſtant of which I ſpeake vnto yee, will not bee though expired. How! Lord, shall I perſever to offend thee ever? know I not, that thou art juſt to all Eternity, and hence is it, that thou punisheſt
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:27009:48"/>
ſinners with torments, which ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue no limits. To burne eternally! Oh how the fire which brought Saint Laurence to ashes, doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite mee to meditate on eternall flames, on, to bee deprived Lord, for ever, of the pleaſures had in glory! Oh! how the burthen of thy croſs is ſweet, and light: if it bee compared with the paines of our privation, which never will haue end: I can ſay no more, I can goe no further. It's neceſſary, that I meditate on this ſo ſerious a ſubiect.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:27009:49"/>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:27009:49"/>
               <head>AN ALARVM FOR LADYES.</head>
               <head>The ſixt Dayes Worke.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T's read; that the Tyrians were forty dayes, whithout shutting their eyes, for reſt: the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall alarum's were ſuch vnder which they liu'd; where they ſaw themſelues, together with their
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:27009:50"/>
towne become cenders.</p>
               <p>Oh! Ladies, how can yee cloſe vp an eye, within the trenches of perpetuall feare, miſery, and cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, where the direfull ſound of this Trumpet for judgment, doth hold the moſt ſtout, the moſt bold in awe, and dread. This heere, doth not menace one ſole burning to ashes: but rather; a thouſand death's together. Further; the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are to bee for ever. Then, rouſe your ſelues; and ſince yee can not gaineſay this eternall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity to dye: dye valiantly with armes in your hands. The benefit thereby had, is companion of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
               <p>Amidſt all the tortures, which cruelty hath invented ever, it's e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed that thereis never any of
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:27009:50"/>
more rigour: then that it of wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching. What an vnquietneſs is it to ſleep never? But if ſo bee it, that for having ſlept too much in this world, yee prooue condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to watch inceſſantly in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: what affliction ſay I, is it, to bee kept awake. I meane not on your downe beds, your deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate coutches well made, and in curious order: but rather on beds of fire, of flames, which by De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine vertue, will burne without conſuming yee? I tremble for feare, yea even to horrour, each time wherein, I meditate heeron.</p>
               <p>I find not any thing of leſs worth in life: then is ſleep; and they who haue compared it to death; therein haue found as pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnant reaſon: as proportion. It's
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:27009:51"/>
true; wee daily dye; but when the new death of fleep doth ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpriſe vs, can not wee ſay: that wee dye twice, at once? Our ſoules haue ſomewhat to doe, to handle in their follies, the life of dreames, wherewith they are then all taken vp, it's a kind of death vnto them as prooveth the light of reaſon, which doth onely rule their facultyes: in ſo much as that; they who ſleep much, are more ſottish then others, and alſo mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ſubject to a ſuddaine death, as if ſo that their continuall action dying twice, did conferre vnto this heavy accident. I returne vnto yee.</p>
               <p>At lenght, God bee thank'd, yee are awakened. How meane yee to paſs the reſt of the dayes
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:27009:51"/>
journey? I am aſſur'd, that yee ought to haue leiſure to bee dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>s'd; atleaſt conſider amidſt theiſe vaine entertainements, the deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable manner of life yee liue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, day, and night, namely; to cloth, and vncloth your miſerable carcaſſes; whilſt Time hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared each one's ſepulcher.</p>
               <p>Il'e tell yee yet againe; that the trade vnder which yee are ever apprentiſes, is a lamentable ſtate, and beeing. Liue yee not a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge life, to change your clothes very often? there's each day ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what to ſay; for the manner of them, differ: in ſo much as, what is now in fashion, hardly will ſuite with yee, and ſerue your tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to morrow, ſo certaine is the world in it's inconſtancy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as are
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:27009:52"/>
your humours.</p>
               <p>Ladyes; there are not found other clothes which change not fashion: but your winding shee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes; they allwayes are the ſame: but; as each one chooſeth the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour's they beſt like of; if your mournefull one's, agree not with your preſent humours, yet accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me your ſelues therevnto, taking your meaſures of them each night in your beds: the ground therein to be found, and the neceſſity, will render vnto yee in the end, an object, which will ſuite with yee, not diſtaſt yee a jot. Ah, no.</p>
               <p>I neither enquire whither, nor to what places yee direct your ſteps, your paces in your carot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; the weither is ſo faire: that
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:27009:52"/>
it inviteth yee to goe abroad, and take the aire. I will attend yee with my thoughts, according to my wonted manner; to know the ſubiect, and ground of your time's enternainement, what it may prooue to bee.</p>
               <p>Behould yee in a curious gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, there ſeated nigh a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, vnder the shaddow of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny trees, whoſe branches on their tops are joyned together, or very nigh. Your intentions in ſo doeing are to lend your gracious eares a while vnto the nightingale: but the letter's ſenſe of her warblings, I muſt declare vnto yee; shee telles yee in her language, in her man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, ſuch as it is: that it's good to ſalute the Sunne each morning, likewiſe in the evening. To ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:27009:53"/>
vnto the Moone ſome curious muſick or other. Theiſe maling Planetts deſiſt not by the influen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of their cours, to giue a ſpeedy end vnto her Kingdome; in ſuch ſort, that her shouts, her turnes, her diviſions, her quaverings, and redoublings are ſo many griefes on the vnhappineſs of her ſtate: ſince that shee hath no voice: but to invite the world to her funerall rites, hence is shee conſtrain'd to dye the ſooner, through the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of her ſinging.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe the Turtell, who ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in vaine her companion, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menteth her miſfortune in an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tune: which doth shew vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to yee: that Time is greedily ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, after the ruine of each thing. And though that the Eccho, bee
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:27009:53"/>
but a ſound, a voice; Time beeing vnable to make it ceaſe, by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees devoureth the rockes, which giue it a rebound. No, no Ladyes; Time doth not forbeare any thing. What though Time were decev'd once; as it is mention'd in the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, when Orpheus requir'd of Him Euridices? Time hath had memorable reveng, as may bee ſeen in the Hiſtoryes of all the Poets, who to that end gaue him their counſailes.</p>
               <p>But how well are yee placed? it ſeemeth to mee; that it's to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate at your eaſe, and repoſe on that all, which God Allmighty hath created heere below, and that it all doth participate of the ſame nature that doe the flowers, and fountaines which yee ſee, ſince
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:27009:54"/>
that all glideth like to the ſwift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their waves, paſſages, their currants.</p>
               <p>Yes, Ladyes, the World is a garden of flowers, various in their graces, their beautyes, colours, and their odours: but all theiſe according to Nature, are of the ſame matter. Il'e declare my ſelf more clearely. God Allmighty in the ſpace of his Creation, planted all what ſoever yee admire heere below, in the garden of the Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, namely; flowers of diuers colours, allſo of valiew: but all of the ſame matter: for; there is not one of them exempt from cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption. Theiſe truely are the flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers diſclos'd in the morning, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playd at midday, faded in the eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and of which Time, who
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:27009:54"/>
is the gardener, croppeth what hee will, and then, when it beſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth him.</p>
               <p>Certes, Ladyes, the world is a fountaine, and whatſoever it's com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of are its waues, which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly haue nothing in their nature, but ſwiftneſs paſſing by. This is eſſentiall, to what ſoever that's heere below. Yee may pleaſe your ſelues, to caſt your eyes, on all the objects, which yee find every where about yee. There is not one onely, which doth not returne yee the like adieu which yee giue them: ſince that yee runne the ſame race all together, though di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſely, and by different wayes, and manner, into the gulphe of the tomb.</p>
               <p>For all that hitherto hath been
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:27009:55"/>
ſay'd; make vnto yee, a poſy of flowers: but in gathering thoſe flowers-deluces, thoſe roſes, thoſe pincks, and gilly-flowers, thinck that Time likewiſe, is daily buſy in the gardens of your faces, there cropping ſometimes; the flower-deluce of your paintings; other times; the roſes of your cheekes; then; the gilly-flowers of your lipps: Whereof hee compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth a noſegay of your inconſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyes. Yee ſenſibly apprehend this verity, other proofes are not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite.</p>
               <p>How now, Ladyes? All theiſe will fade in your ſights, like a flower. All theiſe will glide befo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re your ſelues as waues, and yee as if inſenſible, will not ſtirr a jot, no, not a jot, never, nor reflect the leaſt on the neceſſity of dying:
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:27009:55"/>
from which, God Almighty after the delivery of the law, would not exempt himſelf, no, not him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. But if the ſole thought of death amaze yee; meditate a little, how our ſweete Saviour hath the firſt quenched, the thirſt within the Chalice, which hee preſented, to the end; that at once hee might take from yee both feare, and bit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terneſs, acquitt yee of ſuch like weakneſſe. Death is not terrible: but to the impious. It's true; that it oftentimes aſtonisheth the moſt juſt, through apprehenſions of Gods judgment: but by degrees, this feare becommeth weaker, through the faculty of their rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, having much more hope of mercy: then feare of juſtice, their conſciences, will them ſoe; in ſuch
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:27009:56"/>
manner, that in their agonyes, Nature is ſole Authour of the fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, wherewith they are shaken. Truely; I know not where I am heerein. But what is that which I heare? it's the great bell of the town, which giveth yee notice: that the gates thereof will ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bee shut.</p>
               <p>Ladyes, why lend yee not like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the eares of your imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to the noyſe of this Trumpet of judgment, which never ceaſeth, and doth advertiſe yee: that the gates of Paradiſe are at the point of beeing shut for all Eternity, and that yee shall never enter there: if yee change not your liues. Ah Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity: how thou do'ſt rejoice mee, and jointly aſtonish mee.</p>
               <p>See Ladyes at lenght, your dayes journey hath it's end, and it wlll
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:27009:56"/>
be found to bee well ſpent for your turnes: if ſo that yee haue made your benefits of theiſe important trueths, which I haue ſet before your eyes.</p>
               <p>Even ſo will paſs all the other jorneys of your dayes, to your loſs, and confuſion: if at leaſt, you ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke noe notice of this trueth: that they runne their race they, paſs by. Reflect ſeriouſly with your ſoules on that meditation; and it will prooue impoſſible: that ſpeedily yee make not an accrew of good deedes, an amaſs, in favour of your ſoules. They haue nothing proper to them ſelues: but them onely. They will bee all their treaſures; all their greatneſs, and all their felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, whereof God shall bee the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, the end, the meaſure.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:27009:57"/>If yee knew, Ladyes, the true hearts content, which on enjoyeth, who hath lived well; when ſo one cometh to one's ſtand, abbay, one's laſt end, one's death, yee would la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour with all care, from this inſtant forward in your converſions on which yee would bee more intent. If yee doubt the leaſt of this trueth, and yet, alas! enquire of your ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, how it was with yee, at your laſt ſickneſs. The anxietyes yee had, for your offences, likely increas'd your greifs; and further; ſet before your eyes the joyes, and vnſpeaka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble conforts, wherewith an inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent life might haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſol'd hearts. Truely, I can not conceiue, that there is aught more pleaſant, more delightfull, aſſuredly there's no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in the Vniuers more deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="part">
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:27009:57"/>
               <head>AN ALARVM FOR LADYES.</head>
               <head>The Seauenth, and last Dayes Worke.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>ADYES, how is it with yee? I yet awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken yee againe, I am the ſame this very day in God's name: ſince that hee giveth leaue that this Alarum come to your hands
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:27009:58"/>
to looke on, ſo long as your eares vvill diſpoſe them ſelues to heare attentiuely the harmony therein to bee found for the benefit of your ſoules. I ſpeake to day, as a day of repoſe, wherein yee ought to meditate of happy Eternity, vvhich is propoſed vnto yee for your reward: but; as it is the laſt entertainement, vvhich I am to haue vvith yee; it' is expedient; that I make yee partakers of my ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude; knowing through long ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience the profits vvhich hence yee vvill receaue, bee it, that yee follovv my counſaile. Repreſent your ſelues, make your approatch: for God hath provided, from all Eternity; that this little booke, should fall into your hands, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for your benefits, or for your
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:27009:58"/>
vtter loſſes for your profits; to your benefits; if yee obſerue th' in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions which I giue, and which God himſelf hath inſpired mee with: To your loſſes; if yee shall miſpriſe, what is heerein de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered: this very booke doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince yee of voluntary blindneſs, and declare the admirable fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, which the infinit bounty shall hereby haue shewen vnto yee for your ſafety: it's in yee as yet to chooſe. Il'e tell yee then, for your inſtructions, how profitably yee are to paſs your journey. From the time yee are awakened, let your hearts bee as ſenſible of the new preſent, which God hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven yee this new day: as your eyes are pleaſed, in admiration of his light. Then; vvithout merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizing
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:27009:59"/>
vvith your beds, vvhat ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me yee vvill further aſſigne to your ſelues, for your ſluggiſneſs get out of them, and as ſoone as yee are on your knees before a Crucifix, make that it your loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinglaſſes; it's there where yee may indeed become in loue with your ſelues, weighing your va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liew by the price of that blood, vvhich hath bought yee: O rare miroir! Oh! lookinglaſs to admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re indeed!</p>
               <p>Render thanks vnto your Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, that yee vvere borne, and for your inſtructions in the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, Apoſtolique, and Roman Faith, as the onely vvay of ſafety. Then; offring vp vnto Him all the cogitations, the vvords, and actions of the journey yee are now
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:27009:59"/>
about, beſeech Him ſubmiſſiuely to illuminate the one, and anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te the other, to governe theiſe, and to bee the object of them all together: ſo farre forth, as what yee shall think, and ſay, may bee received by Him gratefully.</p>
               <p>Let the end of this prayer bee, the beginning of your neceſſary affaires to cloth your ſelues: but entertaine the leaſt time therein that yee can, without trouble, or curioſity. I forbid yee not the pouder: ſince yee are no other; But expreſſely the pomada, and vermillion: For; though theiſe are harmeleſs in themſelues: yet they may prooue pernicious, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed not blameleſs through the ills which they may produce, and; as yee shall haue been found com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plices
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:27009:60"/>
of crimes: ſo likewiſe by conſequence of paines.</p>
               <p>As ſoone as yee are dreſs'd, prepare your ſelues to goe to Maſs, where yee shall perſever to render thanks to God, for an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finity of his gratious favours con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd on yee, nor ever let your ſpirits bee diverted aught from this principall, and Divine object: which yee tooke your ſelues vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, as well by reaſons: as by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cognizance. Preſent your ſelues in ſuch manner; that though God bee in each place, our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, is both in body, and ſoule on the ſame Aultar, where yee offer vp your prayers: It ought to cauſe yee, to bee humbly gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue, and wary, even to the not daring once to turne your heads
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:27009:60"/>
without neceſſity, nor ſpeake one ſingle word, vnleſs compulſarily. At return from Church, each one hath ſomewhat to entertaine their times with according to their qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lityes, never to bee found idle, expecting dinner time: where gormandizing, will bee remar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked for an offence ſo diſgracefull in a yong Gentlewoman: as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>normous before God. Shee, who therein can not command her ſelf, is a ſlaue all her life.</p>
               <p>Are yee invited to a feaſt, goe thither: but ſo, that it prooue a banquet for yee, as neither ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, nor drinking beyond your ordinary cuſtome: hence yee will find, that your bodyes will bee the more ſound, more healthy, and your ſoules more innocent. If
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:27009:61"/>
after it, yee take a walke; divert your ſelues from ſuch diſcourſes, where no body is intereſs'd: but if one of the company, doth ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke ill of another, all though it bee in jeſt, turne the diſcourſe, in a faire manner, and to the end: that yee may never accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me your eares to well-like aſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, lay'd on any for defects; it beeing, that yee your ſelues are too much charg'd with them.</p>
               <p>If yee paſs the afternoone within your doores, each one of yee, will employ your ſelues with your needle, or read ſome devout booke, to entertaine yee mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re profitably, during the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone. I ſay your booke of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion: as for the eloquent ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, the Romances, and for the
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:27009:61"/>
Comedyes; they are toyes, meere fables: which diſcover in the end, the vndoubted folies of them, who ſoe haue been their advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, and given them eſteeme, therein haue they employed their times, exceeding ill.</p>
               <p>Bee it a holy day; then let this Alarum wherewith I preſent yee, hinder yee from ſleepe, howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver at the Sermon, and doe not yee imitate ſuch, who are devout in fashion, who are weary on good friday, to heare of the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, without conſidering: that this our Devine Saviour, who hath ſuffred thoſe, for your ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, had more patience in his torments: then haue thoſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious had, to heare onely the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citall, which hath been made. Oh
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:27009:62"/>
Lord! for what other crimes doſt thou reſerue the thunderbolts of thy juſtice.</p>
               <p>When the hower, of your reſts doth call on yee, before yee bee vnclothed make your recourſe to conſult, to adviſe ſeriouſly, and moſt attentiuely the laſt time, the ſelf ſame lookinglaſs, it's the Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifix, fix your eyes on it, and there examine your conſciences, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beſeeching God's mercy's par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for all your treſpaſſes, which yee haue donne, during this dayes journey, and that yee may haue grace, to retaine your ſelues from ſinne; that yee may not fall therein againe. There are yee to reſolue ſoe: then with the ſame action; offer vp vnto him, all your deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, and hopes concerning the
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:27009:62"/>
repoſe, and tranquility of your liues: ſo that hee iuſtify the one through his benignity, and the other through his infinite power: but rather; humbly reſigne your wills to his. Obſerue it well: that hee, who knoweth to compoſe him felf well to God's will, is the wiſeſt of the Vniverſe.</p>
               <p>It's that onely ſcience, Ladyes, which can ſeate yee in repoſe. Build not the height of your deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeignes, on the greatneſs of your familyes, nor on the favour of your freinds. I haue ſeen, ſayeth the Prophet, Lords of the Earth, elevated beyond the height of the Cedars of Libany; but a dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſtory to recite, next day haue vanished from myne eyes, and hardly could I find one, who
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:27009:63"/>
conſeru'd ſo much as the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of his having been. The Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourits of the World, are of the ſame nature, they ſolely paſs it by. Their fortune is a ſuddaine flash of lightning, which farre ſurpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth thunder with it's inevitable fall, in ſort ſuch: that if God lay not the firſt ſtone to all your buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, all will fall; there will not bee found aught, but ruine.</p>
               <p>Deſire then never aught: but what is of God; that's to ſay; that what ſoever are your affaires, yee fully referre them all to his Sovraignity, and without mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur to his Devine Providence: ſince that the ordering of all, doth properly appertaine to him. Wish yee to bee Religious, or to bee maried? take vnto yee that
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:27009:63"/>
reſtraint of humility, and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience: my Lord, thy will bee donne. It's the prayer which hee hath taught yee; judg yee whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it ought to be acceptable vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, and whether profitable to yee: End your examinations by a prayer to the Virgin, as well for her particular merit, from whence the flash through admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it's light ſo bright, daze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the ſight of all the quires of Angell's: as allſo, for your ſafety; ſince shee is Advocate, and all puiſſant Mediatreſs, who ſo hath this Virgin in aſſiſtance, will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver perish.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:27009:64"/>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:27009:64"/>
               <head>A PARTICVLAR ADVISE</head>
               <head>For direction of a one's life.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>EVER bee confident in aught but in God: all freindshipps of the World, retaine parcell of it's variable Nature: ſuch an one to day would dye for yee, who to morrow, were yee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed, would not ſo much as
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:27009:65"/>
honour yee, attired in morning: Intereſs is ever found in affections, bee they never ſo pure. Become yee ill favoured, poore, or old, all your great freinds, and who ſo were laſt evening your loyall lovers will even vanish this very morning, and if yee ſend for them, none of them, will bee found at home for yee. Ladyes, it's onely God, who is a perfect lover, and ſuch like freind indeed. Will yee haue proofes of his goodneſs? Hee dyed for yee before yee were borne. Require yee teſtimonyes of his mercy? dayly hee confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red grace on yee. Loue then him onely. Ladyes, confide in none but in him, and yee shall never bee deceived.</p>
               <p>Offer vp your ſelues in all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:27009:65"/>
for God doth replenish the Vniuers. Hee is every where, in ſuch ſort, that hee is witneſs of your actions, to the end, that this conſideration, might retaine yee in the duetye yee owe vnto ſo Saintly, and adorable Majeſty. The moſt conſonant prayer, which yee can offer vp to God, is for your enemyes: ſince hee himſelf hath given yee the pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne, then; when hee was nay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led on the Croſs; where having nothing but His ſpeach free, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved himſelf thereof, to craue par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for thoſe vilains, who brought him to that beeing; that miſery. Oh vnheard of charity! our ſweet Saviour call'd out for mercy for them, the ſelf-ſame, who gaue him gaule, and vinaiger to
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:27009:66"/>
ſquench his thirſt.</p>
               <p>Even then, when in the dead of winter, yee are in your beds shelters, free from could weather, and other domages which might endanger life, ſet before yee, how many poore there bee at this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry inſtant, who haue but a little dunghill-ſtraw, for their beds sheets, and coverlids, without hope, that to morrow they shall bee provided better. Then; conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſome-what further, elevate your ſpirits to an higher pitch; behould; that God hath given vnto yee degrees, exempt from ſuch like miſeryes, mooved by nothing elſe; but his goodneſs, and bounty conferr'd on yee. Truely they are benignityes, which juſtly exact eternall, and gratefull
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:27009:66"/>
notice; I wonder not aught that vnthankfull hence bee punished for ever. Take heed, that yee prooue not of the number.</p>
               <p>Offer vp your ſelues againe as having been the ſame from all Eternity, whom yee are now in the judgment of God Allmighty. And what yee ought to ponder more ſenſibly, is; that amidſt the infinity of ſoules, his power All<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty doth create daily, hee hath ſelected your's, to bee inſtructed in that Religion, wherein ſolely yee may find your ſafetyes. I am confuſed, nay rather extaſed, jointly each time, I conſider on ſuch venerable truethes, and ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.</p>
               <p>What a wonder of goodneſs is it, that God hath loved yee wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thin
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:27009:67"/>
himſelf in your nothing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all ages I ſay loved yee, even to the conferring on yee a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſortes of benignityes, of which many other's of your ſexe are deprived. Adore yee; adore yee, Ladyes, this Devine Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, which in ſuch manner hath ordained in your favour wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thout your retributes, without your deſerts.</p>
               <p>Bee not yee proud of the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable qualityes, which yee poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs aboue your companions: leaſt that God punnish yee, and take vengeance on yee for it. If yee bee very faire: bee yee likewiſe very humble, to the end, that the world may honour yee: when yee can not bee beloved more. How many haue I known, who
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:27009:67"/>
in one ſelf ſame day, were highly pris'd, mervailouſly eſteem'd of, and jointly admired for piety by all the world. Humility in Ladyes hath more winning grace in it ſelf: then all the guifts of Nature join'd together.</p>
               <p>In all your good deeds; let not Paradiſe bee the ſole object, and ſcope of your workes: for as intereſſed, and mercenary, yee would looſe parcell of their me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits: but ſay with Saint Auguſtine; Lord, were it even ſo, that thou hadſt not a Paradiſe to beſtow, I would not deſiſt to loue thee ſolely: for thou art perfectly amia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; and further, by meanes of loving thee, I feele to my advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, the delights of the ſelf ſame Paradiſe, which thy mercy ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:27009:68"/>
mee to hope for. My Lord, following on, alſo; I should not ceaſe to feare thee, hadſt thou not a Hell to punish mee: ſince that each time I offend thee, I find my ſelf inceſſantly tormented, and I beginne to ſuffer the paines whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rewith thy juſtice doth menace mee. Ladyes, good is to bee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved for it ſelf, and, as God Allmighty is the fountaine there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, yee muſt forbid your hearts that they never ſighe, but for the loue of him if ſo yee will that the very Angells bee paſſionate in your behalfs.</p>
               <p>Bee not yee one of thoſe faint-hearted, who wax pale; and wanne for feare, when one tells yee of death; nay farre otherwiſe; like of the diſcours well, and the
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:27009:68"/>
meditations thereon, to the end that yee may accuſtome your ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues betimes, to paſs that over fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely; which yee muſt vndergoe of neceſſity, namely; finish the worke, which yee haue begun, from the firſt moment of your li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, and wherein yee goe on in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſantly. Oh how terrible is death to them who never haue medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thereon!</p>
               <p>Let then each of yee shew your ſelues oftentimes, vnto your ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues in ſome private retire: and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire where yee shall bee hence fiftie yeares to come, more, or leſs, and elevate your ſpirits on this ſerious ſubject. Yee ſee what it delivereth: It's true, that then the ſame bodyes; which now ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue ſoules, and on which even now
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:27009:69"/>
ſet ſo great a valiew will become no other then hillockes of dung, where the wormes will make their ſeate. But what will become of your ſoules? wherewith will they entertaine their times during this long Eternity? Is it that they muſt burn in Hell in expiation of their crimes? At theiſe laſt words breake your ſilence, and if yee bee in a retired place, where yee can not bee heard, cry, out aloud, and boldly with Saint Auguſtin, ſay. <hi>Lord, burn, cut in pieces, and reduce into pouder, this miſerable body of my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, I abandon it before the fury of thy juſtice; ſo that thou pardon my ſoule in the other.</hi> Ladyes, Oh! what mervailes would theiſe words pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce recited often, for the aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of your ſafetyes: but in it,
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:27009:69"/>
experience will make yee ſenſible of much more then can I heereon deliver.</p>
               <p>I end here with this laſt adviſe, which I offer vp vnto yee, as one of the moſt importants, and of moſt benefit: that yee take vnto yee a particular devotion to the Virgin, daily ſaluting her with ſome Hymne in her praiſe. On whom one of the devout cryeth out; that the Angells bow vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, the Heaven humbleth it ſelf vnto, and that all Nature trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth with honour, and feare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this incomparable Marie; ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce that her womb ſerved for a cradle to her Creatour, her breſts for nouriture, and her armes for a reſt. Truely; she who perfectly knoweth to honour her; is not
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:27009:70"/>
aught wanting, in what shee ought to vnderſtand, for the good of her ſafety.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:27009:70"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
